

💌 axel.faes@gmail.com | 🌴 theaxec.github.io | 🖸 TheAxeC | 🛅 axelfaes | 🗲 Scholar | 🏛 KULeuven Who's Who

Abstract

I am a Msc. Artificial Intelligence and Msc. Computer Science Engineering student at KU Leuven. My main interests include algebraic effect handlers, program optimization, type systems, graph theory, artificial intelligence, neural computing and brain-computer interfaces. I am participating in the Honoursprogramme of the Faculty of Engineering Science (research track) at KU Leuven. I am also a big supporter of Open Source Software.

Research Interests ____

Programming Language Theory Algebraic Effect Handlers, Type Systems and Program Optimization **Artifical Intelligence** Machine Learning, Reinforcement Learning and Virtual Reality

Neuroscience Neural Computing and Brain Computer Interfaces

Educational background

Doctoral Programme in Biomedical Science (PhD) in Computational Neuroscience

Leuven, Belgium

Sep. 2018 - Sep. 2022

Brain-computer interfaces and Neural Engineering

Advanced Master of Science in Engineering (M.Sc.) in Artificial Intelligence

Leuven, Belgium

Sep. 2017 - Jul. 2018 KUTEUVEN

Engineering and Computer Science

Master of Science in Engineering (M.Sc.) in Computer Science (Burgelijk Ingenieur - ir.)

Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2016 - Jul. 2018

Artificial Intelligence & Theoretical Computer Science

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) in Computer Science (79% - Magna Cum Laude)

Hasselt, Belgium

UHASSELT

Sep. 2013 - Jul. 2016

Physics and General courses

Business Summer School: United in Manchester (0739)

Manchester, UK

THE UNIVERSITY OF MANCHESTER

Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

International Business

KUTEUVEN

Honors & Awards

Mar. 2018 Finalist, Cyber Security Challenge Oct. 2017 Honoursprogramme, of the Faculty of Engineering Science

Brussels, Belgium KU Leuven, Belgium

Sep. 2017 3rd place, ICFP 2017 Student Research Competition

Oxford, UK

Jul. 2016 Bachelor Award, in Computer Science

UHasselt, Belgium

May. 2016 3rd place, ACM CHI 2016 Student Design Competition (Interaction Design and User Experience.)

San Jose, CA, USA

Feb. 2016 **2nd place**, BeGDC (Belgian Game Development Championship)

Brussel, Belgium Brussel, Belgium

Jan. 2016 IELTS, Academic Module (8.0/9.0)

Work & Research Experience _____

Phd Candidate (FWO-Aspirant Fellowship)

Leuven, Belgium Oct. 2018 - Current

KU LEUVEN

· Project: "Graph-based model of information diffusion in the human brain for studying event-related potentials"

- Promoter: Prof. Marc van Hulle
- Group: Computational Neuroscience, Laboratory for Neuro-and Psychophysiology, KU Leuven

JULY 12, 2018 AXEL FAES · CURRICULUM VITAE

Student Job: Creating System Identification course

otalicine dobt creating dystem racintineation cours

KU Leuven Sep. 2017 - Current

- Faculty of Engineering Science: ESAT (Electrical Engineering)
- · Research group: STADIUS

Research Assistant: design of type-&-effect system for Eff based on row polymorphism

Leuven, Belgium Apr. 2017 - Oct. 2017

Leuven, Belgium

KU LEUVEN

- Faculty of Engineering Science: Computer Science
- Research group: DTAI
- Part of the Honoursprogramme of the Faculty of Engineering Science (research track).
- Topic: Development of an row-based type-&-effect system for the Eff programming language

Research Assistent: efficient compilation of algebraic effect handlers

Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2016 - Apr. 2017

KU LEUVEN

• Faculty of Engineering Science: Computer Science

- Research group: DTAI
- Part of the Honoursprogramme of the Faculty of Engineering Science (research track). My project is part of the C1 project: Algebraic Effect
 Handlers: Harnessing the Fundamental Power of Effects. Eff is a functional programming language that uses handlers to handle all kinds
 of effects. These effects could be I/O, exceptions, user-defined, etc. My task is to design, implement, benchmark and formally proof new
 optimisations in the Eff compiler. The compiler is written in OCaml.

Web Performance Research Internship

Hasselt, Belgium

EXPERTISE CENTRE FOR DIGITAL MEDIA (EDM), UHASSELT

Jul. 2016 - Sep. 2016

- · I worked on the iMinds PRO-FLOW project.
- My work involved creating multiple usecases to measure website performance. The main focus is on the difference between the http versions (http1.1, https, http2).
- During the project, I had to utilise multiple servers, maintain and extend the nodejs framework used to measure website performance, and manually optimize commercial websites using PHP, JS, HTML and CSS.

Summer Research Internship Physical Computing

Hasselt, Belgium

EXPERTISE CENTRE FOR DIGITAL MEDIA (EDM), UHASSELT

Aug. 2015 - Sep. 2015

Sep. 2014 - Current

Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2016

• Work on a project which focuses on the interaction between a human entity and a drone, aswell as interaction between the drone and virtual objects. This project is written in C++, used the Optitrack motion capture and a custom created drone.

Extracurricular Activities

KU Leuven Leuven, Belgium

DJANGOGIRLS COACH Mar. 2018 - Current

- · We inspire women to fall in love with programming.
- Django Girls organize free Python and Django workshops, create open sourced online tutorials and curate amazing first experiences with technology.

KU Leuven Leuven, Belgium

STUDENT REPRESENTATIVE Sep. 2017 - Current

- POC of Master Computer Science Engineering
- POC of Advanced Master Artificial Intelligence
- Member of Departmental council of Computer Science
- Member of Department board of Computer Science
- Member of Faculty council of Engineering Science

CoderDojo Belgium Uasselt, PXL

Coach

• Teach children how to program utilising Scratch, Python, Minecraft and Lego mindstorm.

Student Council UHasselt

Member of Board of Education

• Member of Faculty Council

MEMBER

- Member of Board of Student Facilities
- Member of Diversity Commission
- Temporary representative in WS (Vlaamse Vereniging van Studenten vzw)

Student Council UHasselt

Мемвек Mar. 2015 - Auq. 2015

- · Member of Board of Education
- Member of Faculty Council
- Member of Board of Student Facilities

JULY 12, 2018 AXEL FAES · CURRICULUM VITAE 2

UHAsselt Hasselt, Belgium

Student Representative Sep. 2013 - Jul. 2016

- · Representing students interests in a Computer Science education context.
- · This meant discussing with the university in order to improve teaching, learning, assessment and academic services.
- Representing Computer Science education for high school students

Natural Languages

English Fluent (IELTS: 8.0/9.0)

Dutch Mothertongue

French Basic Knowledge

Projects

An Information Theoretical Approach to EEG Source-Reconstructed Connectivity

Leuven, Belgium

ADVANCED MASTER'S THESIS

Feb. 2018 - Jul. 2018

This thesis takes an information theoretical approach, which concerns model-free, probability based methods such as Conditional Mutual Information, Directed Information, and Directed feature information. We will investigate how these measures are affected by volume conduction, using as ground truth connectivity between simulated cortical sources in the brainstorm toolbox. In order to validate our methods further, these tools will also be compared with their statistical counterparts such as partial correlation, granger causality and dynamic causal modelling.

Algebraic Subtyping for Algebraic Effects and Handlers

Leuven, Belgium

MASTER'S THESIS

Feb. 2018 - Jul. 2018

• Extending Algebraic Subtyping to incorperate support for algebraic effects and handlers

Reinforcement Learning Agent in Google Deepmind's StarCraft II Framework - CSAI

Leuven, Belgium Feb. 2018 - Jul. 2018

DEVELOPER

• Implement several learning algorithms in PySC2

Software Architecture course - Project

Leuven, Belgium

DEVELOPER

Feb. 2017 - Jul. 2017

Project made for the course 'Software Architecture'. The goal was to design a software architecture in UML for a IoT-platform concerning pluggable sensors. The platform allows storage of customer data and the use of third party applications for data analytics. Final score - 18/20

ICAL parser for KU Leuven schedules

Leuven, Belgium

LEAD DEVELOPER

Aug. 2016 - Current

• An nodejs application to create an iCalender file for courses at KU Leuven. Allows the creation of a schedule containing courses from different masters and the option to ignore events.

Machine learning techniques for flow-based network intrusion detection systems

Hasselt, Belgium

BACHELOR'S THESIS

Feb. 2016 - Jul. 2016

• The thesis gives an overview of how machine learning algorithms could be used for intrusion detection using only IP Flows. The system has been used to detect intrusions in Cegeka Hasselt Datacenter network.

Software engineering: Search and Recommendation System

Hasselt, Belgium

Теам Мемвек

Feb. 2016 - Jul. 2016

A search and recommendation system for VoD (Video on Demand) for Androme. The system is currently being used in production in the Nebula
project. Both Content-Based Recommendations and Collaborative filtering techniques were implemented. Made in a team of 5 (Pieter Teunen,
Luuk Raaijmakers, Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes, Matthijs Kaminski, Wouter Bollaert) utilising Java and the Spring framework. Final score - 15/20

TTUI: Household Survival Hasselt, Belgium

RESEARCHER

Sep. 2015 - Dec. 2015

- Project made for the class 'Technologies and Tools for User Interfaces'.
- A tower-defense style game written in Unity utilising Optitrack motion capture. The game combines the virtual world and reality, by allowing users to interact with the virtual world using real-world objects. Made by Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes and Matthijs Kaminski. Final score 18/20

Cardinal: scripting language

Hasselt, Belgium

LEAD DEVELOPER

Jan. 2015 - Sep. 2015

- Cardinal is a small, fast, class-based, Object Oriented scripting language written in C. It is built upon the skeleton of an existing scripting language and shows how I can modify and improve existing software, as well as design new components to this software.
- · New components include a debugger, an embedding API, multiple inheritance and a new module system.

United in Manchester Manchester, UK

Team Leader Jul. 2015 - Aug. 2015

A summer school which focuses on teamwork in cross-cultural and multidisciplinary teams, global product development and entrepreneurship.
 Our team developed a start-up idea on Food Management/Delivery system. Product pitch took place at the end of the course for feedbacks from professionals and for potential commercialisation. Our team consisted of Axel Faes, Linh Chi Evelyn Phan, Reinaert Van de Cruys and Maria Barouh.

PSOPV: Visual Programming IDE

Hasselt, Belgium

DEVELOPER

Feb. 2015 - Jul. 2015

 A Visual programming IDE created by Axel Faes & Matthijs Kaminski for a course of Hasselt University. The purpose of the IDE is to create 'black boxes' which can send events (signals packed with data) to eachother. We take the idea of using drag-able blocks in a visual IDE and expand on it. Final score - 17/20

Publications

CONFERENCE PAPERS

- Robin Marx, Maarten Wijnants, Peter Quax, Axel Faes, Wim Lamotte, "Web Performance Characteristics of HTTP/2 and comparison to HTTP/1.1", International Conference on Web Information Systems and Technologies, pg 87-114.
- **Robin Marx, Peter Quax, Axel Faes and Wim Lamotte**, "Concatenation, embedding and sharding: Do HTTP/1 performance best practices make sense in HTTP/2?", WEBIST 2017 Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Web Information Systems and Technologies.

EXTENDED ABSTRACTS

Work.

- Axel Faes and Tom Schrijvers, "Towards a Core Language with Row-Based Effects for Optimised Compilation", International Conference on Functional Programming 2017 Student Research Competition.
- **Kashyap Todi, Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes and Matthijs Kaminski**, "Purpose-Centric Appropriation of Everyday Objects as Game Controllers", CHI EA '16: Extended Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. Late Breaking
 - Kashyap Todi, Donald Degraen, Brent Berghmans, Axel Faes, Matthijs Kaminski and Kris Luyten, "Household Survival:
- [5] Immersive Room-Sized Gaming Using Everyday Objects as Weapons", CHI EA '16: Extended Abstracts of the SIGCHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems. Student Game Competition.

THESIS

- [6] Axel Faes, "Algebraic Subtyping for Algebraic Effects and Handlers", Master's Thesis 2018.
- [7] Axel Faes, "Machine learning techniques for flow-based network intrusion detection systems", Bachelor's thesis 2016.

Posters

Axel Faes and Tom Schrijvers, "Towards a Core Language with Row-Based Effects for Optimised Compilation", International Conference on Functional Programming 2017 Student Research Competition.

OTHER PUBLICATION

[9] **Matija Pretnar, Amr Hany Shehata Saleh, Axel Faes and Tom Schrijvers**, "Efficient compilation of algebraic effects and handlers", 2017 - CW Reports, CW708, 32 pp. Leuven, Belgium: Department of Computer Science, KU Leuven..

TALKS, PRESENTATIONS AND OTHER MEDIA

- Sep. 19, 2017 "Honours student Axel Faes wins bronze medal in ACM SIGPLAN", KU Leuven, Department of Computer Science.
- Sep. 19, 2017 "Student Axel Faes wins bronze medal in the ACM SIGPLAN Student Research Competition in ICFP conference", KU Leuven, Department of Computer Science, DTAI.